Hi, this is Matt Baker. Today, I'm going
to show you the family tree of Bohemian
monarchs. But, before I do that, I want
to explain the difference between this
type of Bohemian and this type of
Bohemian. You see, nowadays, the word
Bohemian is mostly used to refer to a
certain kind of lifestyle, one that is
very unconventional and free-spirited,
often associated with artists and
writers. It was this sort of Bohemian
that Freddie Mercury was referencing in
the title of his song Bohemian Rhapsody.
But, you see, originally, the word
Bohemian simply meant someone from the
main part of what we now call the Czech
Republic or Czechia. From the
perspective of Western Europeans, the
traveling Romani people came from that
direction, and therefore, anyone who
adopted a Romani-like lifestyle was
called a Bohemian. But, it's the
original Bohemians that we'll be looking
at in this video, in particular, the
monarchs of the medieval kingdom of
Bohemia. I'll be using our European
Royal Family Tree North/East Chart,
which is available from our website
usefulcharts.com.
You can find a direct link in the
description or pinned comment.
According to legend, the first ruler of
the Czech people was a man named Krok.
Krok had three daughters named Kazi,
Teta, and Libuše. Although she was the
youngest, Libuše was also the wisest,
and therefore, Krok chose her to be his
heir. One day, while looking at a hill,
she saw a vision of a great city, and
therefore, ordered a new castle to be
built there. This ended up being the
city of Prague. Libuše married a simple
plowman called Přemysl, who went on to
become the namesake of the first
Bohemian dynasty, which starts with
seven more legendary rulers. Now, the
interesting thing about this legendary
genealogy is that if you string all the
names together, it actually forms a
coherent sentence in Old Slavonic that
translates as follows: "Halt your steps,
Tetha, and instead think, I do not want
war and wish no evil upon you. Although
we do not bow to the cross, we welcome
you as guests." You see, the person who
came up with the legendary genealogy was
a 12th-century priest named Cosmas. The
thinking is that Cosmas found an old
document relating to a conflict with the
nearby Franks and mistook it for a list
of early rulers. The actual first ruler
of Bohemia, at least according to
verifiable records, was a duke named
Bořivoj. He lived during the time when
the Western Slavs were converting to
Christianity under the guidance of the
Byzantine missionaries Cyril and
Methodius. Cyril is the namesake of the
Cyrillic alphabet, although take note
that he himself did not invent it, but
rather it was his subsequent disciples.
Now, during the reign of Bořivoj,
Bohemia was actually a vassal state of
Moravia, which is today the eastern part
of the Czech Republic. However, during
the next few generations, that situation
reversed, and it ended up being Bohemia
that would control Moravia all the way
up until 1918.
The next important name to point out is
Bořivoj's grandson Wenceslaus I,
who is the namesake of the famous
Christmas carol "Good King Wenceslas".
However, Wenceslaus was not actually a
king during his lifetime. You see, he
was assassinated by his brother
Boleslav, and after this was quickly
venerated as a saint with all sorts of
legends forming about him. Only decades
later did the Holy Roman Emperor Otto
the Great posthumously give him the
title of king.
Boleslav actually ended up becoming a
good ruler, continuing to make Bohemia
into an important regional power. He
also developed closer ties with Rome as
opposed to Constantinople, which would
become important not only to Bohemia,
but to Poland also. You see, his
daughter married Duke Mieszko the first,
and because of this, she ended up
playing a major role in the
Christianization of Poland.
Bohemia's ties to Western Europe were
strengthened even more around the time
of Oldřich, when it became an official
vassal state of the Holy Roman Empire.
But take note that at this point,
Bohemia was still a duchy and not yet a
kingdom. Even when Vratislav and then
later Vladislaus the second were made
kings as rewards for supporting the
emperor, in both cases the title was for
their lifetime only, not hereditary. The
date when Bohemia became a hereditary
kingdom was 1212, during the reign of
Ottokar the first. This was right in the
middle of the conflict between the Welfs
and the Hohenstaufens over who should be
emperor. Ottokar supported the
Hohenstaufen candidate, Frederick the
second, and thus when the Hohenstaufens
won, Bohemia was given a new special
status within the Holy Roman Empire. Not
only was the Bohemian ruler made a
hereditary king, he was also made the
highest ranking prince elector. The next
king, Wenceslaus the first, not to be
confused with good king Wenceslaus, had
the unfortunate privilege of having to
deal with the Mongol invasions into
Eastern Europe. He ended up fending them
off, but only because they retreated in
order to go choose a new great khan. He
also transitioned Bohemia into a more
Western European style kingdom, and was
the first to allow ethnic Germans to
settle there.
But it was his son, Ottokar the second,
who ended up becoming the greatest of
all the original Premyslid monarchs. He
is remembered as the iron and golden
king. Iron because he militarily
expanded his territory all the way down
to the Adriatic Sea, and golden because
he increased silver mining in his
territory, making Bohemia very rich. He
was also a crusader, participating in
two crusades against the Old Prussians.
During one of these, the city of
Königsberg, modern-day Kaliningrad, was
founded and named in his honor.
Königsberg meaning king's mountain, and
referring to him. Ottokar II even almost
became Holy Roman Emperor. You see, his
reign coincided with the Great
Interregnum, a period in which there was
no Holy Roman Emperor, and he actually
had a very good claim to the title
through his mother, who was a
Hohenstaufen. But, he did not get
elected because the German nobles
actually felt that he was too powerful,
and opted to elect Rudolph of Habsburg
instead, because at the time the
Habsburgs were a very minor house,
something that obviously went on to
change. Rudolph, the new German king,
took away Ottokar's newly acquired
territories, including Austria. So, in a
last attempt to get them back, Ottokar
fought Rudolph at the Battle on the
Marchfeld, which ended up being one of
the largest battles to occur in Europe
during the medieval period. Ottokar
lost, and in fact was killed during the
battle, resulting in his son, Wenceslaus
II, becoming king at just 6 years old.
Wenceslaus II initially married a
Habsburg, Judith of Austria, but upon
her death, he married Elizabeth of
Poland. This gave him a claim to the
Polish throne because her father,
Premyslid II, had managed to unite
Poland and become their first king in
over 200 years. So, in the year 1300,
Wenceslaus II was crowned king of Poland
in addition to Bohemia. The following
year, Andrew III of Hungary died,
resulting in the extinction of the Arpad
dynasty there. Wenceslaus II's mother
had been a descendant of the Arpads,
meaning that Wenceslaus II now had a
claim to Hungary as well. In the end, it
was decided that his 11-year-old son,
the future Wenceslaus III, would be
crowned king of Hungary based on an
agreement that he would eventually marry
Andrew
But, here's what happened. Wenceslaus II
died in 1305, making his now 15-year-old
son, Wenceslaus III, king of all three
kingdoms: Bohemia, Poland, and Hungary.
But, then his betrothal to the Hungarian
princess was called off, and therefore
Wenceslaus III agreed to give the
Hungarian crown to Otto of Wittelsbach,
another Arpad descendant. But, then just
1 year later, Wenceslaus III was
assassinated at age 16, resulting in the
extinction of the Premyslid dynasty. At
this point, Bohemia, Poland, and Hungary
went in three very different directions.
In Poland, Władysław I became king,
followed by Casimir the Great. In
Hungary, Otto was replaced by Charles I
from the Capetian House of Anjou, father
of Louis the Great. And in Bohemia, the
throne went first to Wenceslaus III's
brother-in-law, Henry, and then to his
other brother-in-law, John, from the
House of Luxembourg.
And this was really significant because,
you see, John's father ended up becoming
Holy Roman Emperor, and then later, his
son, Charles, became Holy Roman Emperor
as well, becoming the first person to
hold both the crowns of Bohemia and
Germany. In Bohemia, he was known as
Charles
but as emperor, he was known as Charles
Bohemian monarch of all time. During his
reign, Bohemia experienced a golden age
with Prague becoming the capital of the
Holy Roman Empire, as well as one of the
largest and most prominent cities in
Europe. During Charles IV's reign, the
current St. Vitus Cathedral began to be
constructed, as well as the famous
Charles Bridge, which bears his name.
Charles IV was succeeded by his son
Wenceslaus IV, who served as king of
Bohemia and Germany, but was never
actually crowned as Holy Roman Emperor.
Meanwhile, his half-brother Sigismund
became king of Hungary due to his
marriage to Mary, the daughter of Louis
the Great. Wenceslaus IV ended up being
a rather ineffectual ruler, and as such
was eventually deposed as king of
Germany. With his half-brother
Sigismund, about a decade later, being
elected instead, this time being
actually crowned as emperor. As emperor,
Sigismund is remembered for ending the
papal schism between Avignon and Rome,
and for building defenses against the
growing Ottoman Empire. Now, in Bohemia,
because Wenceslaus IV had no children,
when he died, Sigismund technically
became king there as well. I say
technically because around the same time
that Wenceslaus IV died, the Hussite
Wars began. The Hussites being a group
of sort of proto-Protestants,
and therefore Sigismund wasn't actually
able to take full control of Bohemia
until he made a peace agreement with the
moderate Hussites, just 1 year before
his death.
Now, Sigismund also did not have any
surviving sons, just one daughter named
Elizabeth. And therefore, when Sigismund
died, his titles passed to Elizabeth's
husband, Albert, who was a Habsburg.
Now, this is important because it marks
the beginning of the Habsburgs' near
continuous control of the Holy Roman
Empire for the next 368 years. Let's
briefly switch over to our European
royal family tree west chart so I can
show you where things went from here in
terms of the emperorship. So, here's
Sigismund again and here's his
son-in-law Albert who, as you can see,
was a descendant of King Rudolph of
Habsburg who I mentioned earlier. Albert
was never actually crowned emperor and
died young with no son to succeed him.
Therefore, at this point the next German
king to be elected was his second cousin
Frederick from a different branch of the
Habsburg tree, the one that would
ultimately stay in power leading to
Charles V and his brother Ferdinand.
We'll come back to them in a bit, but
for now let's return to the north/east
chart to continue along the line of
Bohemian kings.
So, when Albert died, Elizabeth was
actually still pregnant with their
firstborn son, Ladislaus. At just 2
months old, he was named King of
Hungary, although this was contested by
Władysław III of Poland. However, in
Bohemia there was actually no king for
the next 13 years with the country being
split between Catholic nobles and
Hussite nobles. Eventually, a Hussite
leader by the name of George of
Poděbrady gained the upper hand and
became a regent for the now 13-year-old
Ladislaus V.
But then, when Ladislaus V
died at age 17, George was named king.
However, in Hungary, a man named
Matthias Corvinus was elected instead.
From here we get just two more
independent kings of Bohemia. The first
being Vladislaus II
who was the son of Casimir IV of Poland.
However, through his mother he was the
grandson of Elizabeth of Luxembourg and
Albert of Habsburg. Because of these
genealogical connections, he was given
the throne of Bohemia before he was able
to inherit Poland. And then when
Matthias Corvinus died, he was given
Hungary as well. Finally, when his
father died, he could have become a
triple king, adding Poland to his
realms. But he opted instead to let his
brother John reign there. In Bohemia and
Hungary, he became known as King Dobsha,
Dobsha meaning okay, because he
basically let the nobles do whatever
they wanted and signed every petition
with okay. This lack of strong
leadership led to the weakening of
Hungary in particular, setting the stage
for the Ottomans to make gains there,
which they did during the reign of his
son Louis II. In fact, Louis died at the
Battle of Mohács against the Ottomans,
and from that point onwards, Hungary
would never be the same.
Prior to his death, Vladislaus II agreed
to have his daughter Anne marry a
Habsburg, so that if Louis's line died
out, which it did before it even began,
Bohemia and Hungary would be
incorporated into the Habsburg domains.
So, let's now go back to the West chart
to see that more clearly. So, here's
Vladislaus II on this chart, and here's
his daughter Anne, who married Ferdinand
I, the brother of Charles
Ferdinand became King of Bohemia and
Hungary when Anne's brother Louis was
killed by the Ottomans in 1526.
Now, as you probably know, Charles V
inherited both the Holy Roman Empire and
Spain. But just before he died, he
decided to split his realms, giving the
emperorship to his brother Ferdinand,
and Spain to his son Philip. Therefore,
in 1556, Ferdinand became Holy Roman
Emperor in addition to being King of
Bohemia and Hungary. And from here on
out, those three titles, Holy Roman
Emperor, King of Bohemia, and King of
Hungary, would basically stay together
until the time of Napoleon. The only two
exceptions were in 1619,
when Frederick V of the Palatinate,
known as the Winter King, became King of
Bohemia for about 1 year. And then from
1740 to 1765, when Maria Theresa was
able to become Queen Regnant of both
Bohemia and Hungary, but not a reigning
Empress. Eventually, her husband became
the Emperor, and the line continued
through their sons.
When we get to Francis II,
though, the Holy Roman Empire was
dissolved and replaced in Austria by the
Austrian Empire. Thus, for another
100-plus years, we get the three titles
of Emperor of Austria, King of Bohemia,
and King of Hungary being held together
up until the end of World War I, which
is when all three monarchies were
dissolved. At this point in 1918, the
Czechs and the Slovaks joined together
to create Czechoslovakia, which lasted
until the end of 1992, after which time
it was split into the Czech Republic and
Slovakia.
Okay, so that was a look at the monarchs
of Bohemia. Once again, if you want to
get a copy of the chart as a poster,
just head over to usefulcharts.com,
or simply click the link in the
description, pinned comment, or on
screen right now. Thanks for watching.